Guide to the Alvin Saunders Johnson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Alvin Saunders Johnson papers
1902-1969
MS 615
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.75
(15 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, notes, clippings and photographs of Alvin Saunders Johnson. Although records relating to his career are relatively scanty, two manuscript drafts of his autobiography, Pioneer Progress, are among the writings. The correspondence of some 1,700 letters includes: Max Ascoli, Jacob Billikopf, Gerhard Colm, Agnes DeLima, Thomas E. Dewey, Eduard Heinmann, Edith Johnson, Corliss Lamont, Adolphe Lowe, Thomas Mann, Harry Scherman.
Johnson, Alvin Saunders, 1874-1971
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Alvin S. Johnson, Agnes DeLima, and Mrs. Edith Levy, 1967.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence. II. Biographical and Subject files. III. Writings.
Scope and Contents
The Alvin Saunders Johnson Papers reflect Dr. Johnson's career as a scholar and educational administrator as well as his participation in a variety of humanitarian projects. Unfortunately, the papers contain only a very limited amount of material on Johnson's most important projects—the development of the New School, the University in Exile, the Ecole Libre des Hautes Etudes, and the New York State Commission on Discrimination in Employment. Among the few materials relating to the Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences are a 1953 memorandum on a revision of the Encyclopedia, several letters to Agnes de Lima discussing the project's progress, and correspondence with David L. Sills discussing the Encyclopedia's background. Except for a manuscript copy of his autobiography, Pioneer's Progress, the papers contain almost no material relating to Johnson's teaching career prior to 1917, his work for the Committee of Fifteen, or his years on the New Republic's editorial staff.
The papers are arranged in three series: I. Correspondence; II. Biographical and Subject files; III. Writings.
CORRESPONDENCE, 1902-1969 (predominantly 1930-1965)
BIOGRAPHICAL AND SUBJECT FILES, 1927-1964
WRITINGS, 1907-1966.
Series I, CORRESPONDENCE, contains approximately 1700 letters, many of which are routine. Correspondents of note include:
Max Ascoli (15 from A.J./ 7 to)
Jacob Billikopf (16 from A.J./ 14 to)
Gerhard Colm (20 from A.J./ 7 to)
Agnes de Lima (100 from A.J.)
Thomas E. Dewey (12 from A.J./ 3 to)
Eduard Heimann (17 from A.J./ 2 to)
Edith Johnson (102 from A.J.)
Corliss Lamont (28 from A.J./ 22 to)
Adolph Lowe (22 from A.J./ 3 to)
Thomas Mann (6 from A.J./ 4 to)
Harry Scherman (3 from A.J./ 30 to)
Dr. Johnson's correspondence with Ascoli, Colm, Heimann, Lowe, and Mann deals with refugee scholar problems and New School affairs. The Billikopf, Lamont, and Scherman correspondence discusses primarily New School business and affairs. Johnson's letters to Agnes de Lima are valuable for their comments on the New School, the Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences, and a variety of other projects. The Johnson-Dewey correspondence deals with Johnson's work on the New York State Commission on Discrimination in Employment.
Series II, BIOGRAPHICAL AND SUBJECT FILES, includes several biographical sketches of Johnson, a dozen photographs of Johnson, an incomplete card file of Johnson's articles (1914-1945), and a scrapbook of newspaper clippings relating to his activities (1927-1960). The few subject files include a memorandum on a proposed revision of the Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences (1953); a copy of the final published report of the New York State Commission on Discrimination in Employment (1945); a list of the refugee scholars brought to America through Johnson's efforts.
Manuscript materials in Series III, WRITINGS, includes Johnson's letters to the editor, New School Bulletin editorials, over a hundred essays and addresses dealing with a wide variety of topics, and Pioneer's Progress. Published copies of Johnson's books are also included in this series.
The Alvin Saunders Johnson Papers were donated to Yale University in 1967 by Alvin Saunders Johnson, Agnes de Lima, and Mrs. Edith Levy. Over three hundred of the letters in Series I, CORRESPONDENCE, were solicited by Dr. Johnson from colleagues and friends.
"This I Believe," a recording of Dr. Alvin Johnson by C.B.S., for Edward R. Murrow, is available in the Historical Sound Recordings Collection of Yale University Library.
Biographical / Historical
Alvin Saunders Johnson was born on December 18, 1874, and spent his childhood and youth on a farm in northeastern Nebraska. In 1897 he graduated from the University of Nebraska with an A.B. in the classics. After brief service in the army during the Spanish-American War he went on to study economics at Columbia University where he received his Ph.D. in 1902.
From 1901 to 1917 Dr. Johnson taught successively at Bryn Mawr, Columbia, Nebraska, Texas, Chicago, Stanford, and Cornell. Throughout this period he supplemented his teaching by writing and research. In 1902 Putnam's published The Social Evil, Johnson's study of prostitution which had been undertaken at the request of New York City's Committee of Fifteen. While at Columbia he worked on the International Encyclopedia and contributed economic articles to Political Science Quarterly and the Quarterly Journal of Economics. Articles directed to a more popular audience were published in the Atlantic Monthly and the Unpopular Review. In 1916 Dr. Johnson made a study of public library operations for the Carnegie Corporation.
In 1917, on the eve of America's entry into World War I, Johnson gave up his teaching career and joined the staff of The New Republic as economics editor. The recently launched New Republic was at the time one of the major organs in America for liberal expression. During 1919 Johnson joined a group of New Republic colleagues and Columbia professors, including Charles Beard, James Harvey Robinson, John Dewey, and Wesley Mitchell, in founding the New School for Social Research. For the first several years Johnson served as a New School trustee. However, in 1922, when financial and personal problems threatened to close the school, he took charge and served as the school's director until 1945. Under his vigorous leadership the New School quickly became one of the most eminent and influential centers of adult education in the United States. Notable innovations in the school's curriculum included courses in psychoanalysis and public housing.
During his tenure as Director of the New School Dr. Johnson did not hesitate to assume additional responsibilities. In 1927 he joined forces with Edwin R. A. Seligman to develop and edit the monumental Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences. From 1927 to 1947 he served as a member of the editorial council of the Yale Review and was Professor of Economics and Director of General Studies at the Graduate School of Yale during the 1938-1939 academic year. In 1943, with Governor Thomas E. Dewey's support, Johnson became Vice-chairman of New York State's Commission on Discrimination in Employment. The Commission drafted and helped pass the New York Fair Employment Act of 1945. The act later served as a model for the anti-discrimination legislation of other states.
One of Dr. Johnson's most noted programs was conceived in response to Hitler's dismissal of many prominant scholars from their positions in German universities early in 1933. Johnson's idea was to bring these scholars to America and establish them as a group. Financial support for the project was forthcoming and in October of 1933 the "University in Exile" opened its doors. This group of scholars, composed of some of the most talented social scientists in Europe, was eventually incorporated into the New School as a permanent graduate faculty. During 1940, when the Germans invaded Belgium and France, Johnson again went to the aid of foreign scholars. With the help of the Rockefeller Foundation he succeeded in bringing to America nearly two hundred emminent and promising scholars. In 1942 members of this group joined together to form the Ecole Libre des Haute Etudes which remained part of the New School until it became independent in 1946.
Besides his activities as an educator and administrator Dr. Johnson was also a prolific writer, producing nearly a thousand scholarly and popular articles, several novels, two collections of short stories, and an autobiography. The wide ranging themes of Johnson's writings reflect both his remarkably broad interests and his profound faith in the possibility of human progress through education.
Alvin Saunders Johnson died on June 7, 1971.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
New Republic; Adult education; Economics; Education -- United States -- History; Political refugees; Social sciences -- Dictionaries; Social sciences -- Encyclopedias; World War, 1939-1945; Europe; Germany; New York (State); Authors; Educators; Abrams, Charles, 1901-1970; Ascoli, Max, 1898-1978; Baldwin, Roger N. (Roger Nash), 1884-1981; Baruch, Bernard M. (Bernard Mannes), 1870-1965; Berenson, Bernard, 1865-1959; Billikopf, Jacob, 1883-1950; Brecht, Arnold, 1884-1977; Brooks, Van Wyck, 1886-1963; Colm, Gerhard, 1897-1968; Day, George Parmly, 1876-1959; De Lima, Agnes; Dewey, John, 1859-1952; Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955; Erler, Adalbert, 1904-; Finkelstein, Louis, 1895-1991; Fisher, Dorothy Canfield, 1879-1958; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965; Hand, Learned, 1872-1961; Heimann, Eduard, 1889-1967; Heimedinger, Leo; Hirsch, Julius, 1882-1961; Huxley, Julian, 1887-1975; Johnson, Alvin Saunders, 1874-1971; Kilpatrick, William Heard, 1871-1965; Lamont, Corliss, 1902-1995; Lamont, Thomas W. (Thomas William), 1870-1948; Lehman, Herbert H. (Herbert Henry), 1878-1963; Lerner, Max, 1902-1992; Lowe, Adolph, 1893-; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982; Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955; May, A. Wilfred, 1900-1969; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-1990; Rosenwald, Lessing J. (Lessing Julius), 1891-1979; Rothschild, Robert; Scherman, Harry, 1887-1969; Simons, Hans; New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.: 1919-1997); Yale University -- Faculty
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1902-1969 (predominantly 1930-1965); Series I; 3 linear feet (7 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent or name of organization. Letters of a particular correspondent are organized chronologically and include both incoming and outgoing letters.
  Folders with asterisks (*) contain ten or more items.
  - A - A1, 1935-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Am - Az, 1932-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Abrams, Charles (*), 1945-1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ascoli, Max and Marion (*), 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ba - Bd, 1931-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Be - Bh, 1933-1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bi - Bq, 1933-1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Br - Brh, 1935-1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bri - Bt, 1939-1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bu - Bz, 1939-1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Baldwin, Roger Nash, 1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 10a)
  - Baruch, Bernard (*), 1945-1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Basilius, Harold A. (*), 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Beard, Charles and Mary, 1940-1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Berenson, Bernard, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 13a)
  - Berle, Lena (*), 1956-1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Billikopf, Jacob (*), 1945-1948 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Brecht, Arnold (*), 1943-1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - re: Brecht, Bertolt, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Brooks, Van Wyck (*), 1939-1948 (Box 1, Folder 17a)
  - Ca - Ck, 1935-1959 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - C1 - Com, 1933-1957 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Con - Cz, 1933-1948 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Cohen, Mrs. Henry S. (*), 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Colm, Gerhard (*), 1946-1963 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Da - Dh, 1933-1957 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Di - Dt, 1946-1956 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Du - Dz, 1927-1948 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Day, George Parmly, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 25a)
  - deLima, Agnes (*), 1920-1967 (Box 2, Folder 26-29)
  - Dewey, John (*), 1935-1951 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Dewey, Thomas E. (*), 1946-1955 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - DuBois, W.E.B., 1927 January 13 (Box 2, Folder 31a)
  - Ea - Ek, 1937-1957 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - E1 - Ez, 1940-1966 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Ecole Libre, 1942-1956 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences
    General
    See: box 2, folders 26-29 box 6, folder 114
  - Einstein, Albert (*), 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Erler, Adalbert (*), 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Fa - Fh, 1939-1956 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Fi - Fk, 1933-1953 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Fl - Fq, 1932-1949 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Fr - Fz, 1926-1965 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Finkelstein, Louis, 1947-1961 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Fisher, Dorothy Canfield (*), 1939-1953 (Box 2, Folder 41a)
  - Frankfurter, Felix, 1941-1949 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Ga - Gn, 1933-1949 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Go - Gq, 1935-1952 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Gr - Gt, 1933-1959 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Gu - Gz, 1943-1948 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Ha - Ham, 1932-1948 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Han - Hd, 1932-1955 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - He - Heq, 1946-1962 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Her - Hn, 1946-1956 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Ho - Hoq, 1946-1958 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Hor - Ht, 1933-1961 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Hu - Hz, 1935-1949 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Hand, Learned, 1932, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 53a)
  - Heimann, Edward (*), 1935-1966 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Heimedinger, Leo (*), 1946-1949 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Heineman, Dannie (*), 1947-1956 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Hirsch, Edith (*), 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Hirsch, Julius (*), 1946-1948 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - re: Humanity Loan, 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Huxley, Julian, 1935, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 60a)
  - I, 1935-1963 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - J, 1931-1962 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Jelenko, Therese (*), 1955-1965 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Jelliffe, BeLinda (*), 1947-1949 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Johnson, Edith (*), 1955-1961 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Johnson, Edith (*), 1962-1966 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Johnson Family (*), 1902-1909 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Jung, Leo, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - K - Kd, 1933-1957 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Ke - Kn, 1931-1948 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Ko - Kz, 1945-1956 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Kilpatrick, William Heard, 1933-1948 (Box 4, Folder 71a)
  - La - Ld, 1932-1963 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Le - Lek, 1932-1947 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Lei - Lh, 1934-1963 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Li - Ln, 1932-1956 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Lo - Lz, 1932-1957 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Lamont, Corliss (*), 1936-1963 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Lamont, Thomas W. (*), 1931-1947 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Lehman, Herbert (*), 1931-1956 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Lerner, Max, 1948, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 79a)
  - Longstreth, Natalie, 1956-1969, undated (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Lowe, Adolph (*), 1943-1962 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Lyon, Louise, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Ma - Maf, 1931-1967 (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Mag - Md, 1935-1965 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Me - Mh, 1932-1953 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Mi - Mn, 1935-1954 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Mo - Mt, 1934-1948 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Mu - Mz, 1933-1957 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - MacLeish, Archibald
    See: box 1, folder 17
  - Mann, Thomas (*), 1938-1951 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Maxwell, William Q., 1949-1958 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - May, A. Wilfred (*), 1946-1948 (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - re: Mazzuchetti, Lavinia, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Mumford, Lewis, 1933, undated (Box 5, Folder 92a)
  - N, 1938-1966 (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - New School for Social Research
    See: box 2, folders 26-29 box 6, folder 112
  - New York State Committee on Discrimination
    See: box 2, folder 31 box 9, folder 152
  - O, 1931-1954 (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Pa - Pe, 1933-1952 (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Pf - Pn, 1932-1954 (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - Po - Pz, 1933-1961 (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - Ra - Rh, 1931-1953 (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - Ri - Rn, 1936-1958 (Box 5, Folder 99)
  - Ro - Rz, 1933-1966 (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - Rosenberg, James and Elizabeth, 1945-1948 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Rosenwald, Lessing J., 1945-1948 (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - Rothschild, Baron Robert, de, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 102a)
  - Sa - Sb, 1940-1956 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Sc - Sd, 1933-1956 (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - Se - Sg, 1933-1947 (Box 6, Folder 105)
  - Sh, 1946-1956 (Box 6, Folder 106)
  - Si - S1, 1933-1948 (Box 6, Folder 107)
  - Sm - So, 1923-1953 (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - Sp - Std, 1931-1966 (Box 6, Folder 109)
  - Ste - Stq, 1934-1967 (Box 6, Folder 110)
  - Str - Sz, 1931-1958 (Box 6, Folder 111)
  - Scherman, Harry (*), 1940-1967 (Box 6, Folder 112)
  - Schutz, Alfred (*), 1945-1962 (Box 6, Folder 113)
  - Sills, David L., 1964-1967 (Box 6, Folder 114)
  - Simons, Hans (*), 1946-1959 (Box 6, Folder 115)
  - Sulger, Kurt, 1947-1948 (Box 6, Folder 116)
  - Ta - Th, 1932-1948 (Box 6, Folder 117)
  - Ti - Tr, 1940-1957 (Box 6, Folder 118)
  - Tu - Tz, 1946-1962 (Box 7, Folder 119)
  - U - V, 1931-1963 (Box 7, Folder 120)
  - University in Exile
    See: box 1, folder 4 box 1, folder 17 box 2, folder 35 box 2, folder 36 box 2, folder 42 box 7, folder 128 box 8, folder 145
  - Untermeyer, Jean Starr (*), 1944-1967 (Box 7, Folder 121)
  - Wa - Wd, 1945-1961 (Box 7, Folder 122)
  - We - Wh, 1933-1957 (Box 7, Folder 123)
  - Wi - Wn, 1931-1954 (Box 7, Folder 124)
  - Wo - Wz, 1933-1956 (Box 7, Folder 125)
  - Warburg, Mrs. Felix M. (*), 1946-1956 (Box 7, Folder 126)
  - Weissmandel, Michael B. (*), 1948 (Box 7, Folder 127)
  - re: Wellesz, Egon (*), 1940 (Box 7, Folder 128)
  - Wolfe, Don M. (*), 1948-1967 (Box 7, Folder 129)
  - X - Y - Z, 1946-1963 (Box 7, Folder 130)
  - Yale Review (*), 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 131)
  - Unidentified correspondents, 1933-1967 (Box 7, Folder 132)
- BIOGRAPHICAL AND SUBJECT FILES, 1927-1964; Series II; 1.25 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Series II includes biographical sketches and a newspaper clipping scrapbook arranged chronologically. Subject files are arranged alphabetically with the materials in each folder arranged chronologically.
  - Biographical data (Box 8, Folder 133)
  - Photographs - Alvin and Edith Johnson (Box 8, Folder 134)
  - Awards, honors, tributes (Box 8, Folder 135-136)
  - Reviews of Alvin Johnson's books (Box 8, Folder 137)
  - Card file of articles by Alvin Johnson (incomplete), 1914-1945 (Box 8, Folder 138)
  - Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences memorandum on revision, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 139)
    See also: box 2, folders 26-29 box 6, folder 114
  - International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences, Prospectus, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 140)
  - Hebrew Technical Institute, Directors of, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 141)
  - Longstreth, Natalie "Moses", undated (Box 8, Folder 142)
  - Mann, Thomas "The Living Spirit", 1937 (Box 8, Folder 143)
  - Beard, Charles "Democracy and Education in the U.S." (Box 8, Folder 143)
  - New School - Institute of World Affairs, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 144)
  - New School - Refugee Scholar List, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 145)
  - New School - Report of Director, 1931-1932, 1942-1943 (Box 8, Folder 146-147)
  - New School - publicity pamphlets, 1925-1949, 1951-1963, undated (Box 8, Folder 148-149)
  - New School - press releases, 1940-1959 (Box 9, Folder 150)
  - New School - 25th Anniversary dinner list, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 151)
  - New York State - Report of Commission Against Discrimination, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 152)
  - Pink, Louis H. "An Economic United States of Europe Now", 1946 (Box 9, Folder 153)
  - University in Exile dinner speeches, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 154)
  - New School Bulletin
    - 1927-1928 (Box 9, Folder 155)
    - 1928-1950, 1952-1964 (Box 9, Folder 156-175)
  - Clippings, 1950s, 1960s (Box 10, Folder 176-177)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, undated (Box 10, Folder 178)
  - Clippings, 1927-1949 (Box 10, Folder 179-185)
- WRITINGS, 1907-1966; Series III; 2.25 linear feet (5 boxes)
  Dr. Johnson's writings are arranged in three sections: book reviews and editorials (1933-1960); essays and addresses (1907-1966); books (1909-1965). Within each section items are organized chronologically followed by undated materials.
  - Book Reviews and Editorials
    - Book reviews, 1944-1956 (Box 11, Folder 186)
    - New School Bulletin editorials, 1945-1961, 1933-1944, undated (Box 11, Folder 187-189)
    - Letters to the editor, Herald Tribune, 1951-1954 (Box 11, Folder 190)
    - Letters to the editor, New York Times, 1944-1960 (Box 11, Folder 191)
    - Letters to the editor, miscellaneous, 1940-1957 (Box 11, Folder 192)
    - Letters to the editor re: support of Eisenhower, 1952-1956 (Box 11, Folder 193)
  - Addresses and Essays
    - "Influences Affecting the Development of Thrift", 1907 (Box 11, Folder 194)
    - "The Relation of Monopoly Price to the Rate of Interest", 1908 (Box 11, Folder 194)
    - "An Ethical Aspect of the New Industrialism", 1913 (Box 11, Folder 194)
    - "The Case Against the Single Tax", 1914 (Box 11, Folder 194)
    - "War and the Interests of Labor", 1914 (Box 11, Folder 194)
    - "Memorandum on the Russian Question", [1920?] (Box 11, Folder 194)
    - "Metropolitan Provincialism", 1931 (Box 11, Folder 195)
    - "On the Curriculum", 1931 (Box 11, Folder 195)
    - "For an Ordered Capitalism", 1932 (Box 11, Folder 195)
    - "The Happy Valley", 1933 (Box 11, Folder 195)
    - "Intellectual Liberty Imperilled", 1933 (Box 11, Folder 195)
    - "Security in the Modern Age", 1933 (Box 11, Folder 195)
    - "University in Exile", 1933 (Box 11, Folder 195)
    - "The Coming American Revolution", 1934 (Box 11, Folder 195)
    - "Homesteads and Subsistence Homesteads", 1935 (Box 11, Folder 196)
    - "The Rationale of Autarchy", 1935 (Box 11, Folder 196)
    - "A Reaffirmation", 1935 (Box 11, Folder 196)
    - "Andrew Carnegie, Educator", 1936 (Box 11, Folder 196)
    - "The Greatest Show on Earth", 1936 (Box 11, Folder 196)
    - "The Economist in a World in Transition", 1937 (Box 11, Folder 196)
    - "After the New Deal", 1938 (Box 11, Folder 197)
    - "A People's University", 1938 (Box 11, Folder 197)
    - "The Trend in Economic Science", 1938 (Box 11, Folder 197)
    - "After School and College", 1939 (Box 11, Folder 197)
    - "Assembly of Council of Jewish Federations, Address", 1939 (Box 11, Folder 197)
    - "Instead of the New Deal", 1939 (Box 11, Folder 197)
    - "The Rising Tide of Anti-Semitism", 1939 (Box 11, Folder 197)
    - "Academic Freedom", 1940 (Box 11, Folder 198)
    - "Economic Questions", 1940 (Box 11, Folder 198)
    - "For the Defense of Democracy", 1940 (Box 11, Folder 198)
    - "The Crisis in Education", 1941 (Box 11, Folder 198)
    - "Hitler and American Scholarship", 1941 (Box 11, Folder 198)
    - "The Refugee Scholar in America", 1941 (Box 11, Folder 198)
    - "The Rise of American Cultural Leadership", 1941 (Box 11, Folder 198)
    - "Speech to the Press and Refugee Professors", 1941 (Box 11, Folder 198)
    - "The University in Exile", 1941 (Box 11, Folder 198)
    - "The Coming Organization for Peace", 1942 (Box 11, Folder 199)
    - "Ecole Libre, First Anniversary Address", 1942 (Box 11, Folder 199)
    - "The Educator and the War", 1942 (Box 11, Folder 199)
    - "The Post-War Farmer", 1942 (Box 11, Folder 199)
    - "A Time for World Civilization", 1942 (Box 11, Folder 199)
    - "War and the Scholar", 1942 (Box 11, Folder 199)
    - "Broadcast for OWI", 1943 (Box 11, Folder 200)
    - "New School Commencement Address", 1943 (Box 11, Folder 200)
    - "One Revolution: American and French", 1943 (Box 11, Folder 200)
    - "Prodromes d'un Monde Nouveau", 1943 (Box 11, Folder 200)
    - "The Coming Peace Crisis", 1944 (Box 11, Folder 201)
    - "Hiram J. Halle, Funeral Address", 1944 (Box 11, Folder 201)
    - "The Issues of the Coming Election", 1944 (Box 11, Folder 201)
    - "New School Commencement Address", 1944 (Box 11, Folder 201)